Guide to the Al Allen Collection on the International Longshore and Warehouse Union
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Al Allen collection on the International Longshore and Warehouse Union
1939-2016
1970-1979
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
6028
6028-001
Allen, Al
.72 cubic feet (2 boxes) plus 4 videocassettes
Compiled by Al Allen, a retired longshoremen, the collection contains research materials and correspondence documenting the activities of the International Longshore and Warehouse Union (ILWU) and its members.
Al Allen grew up in San Francisco, Califronia, and entered a career as a longshoreman in International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, Local 10 (San Francisco). In 1959, Allen came onto the "B List" in San Francisco, working as a winch driver. The ILWU created the new hiring category in San Francisco--"B" men worked irregularly and had the dirtiest jobs, with the promise of promotion to "A" status after a year of work, and were not considered full union members until that time. Later in his career there, Allen moved into crane work. Allen was one of the original people to go to work at SeaLand as a supplement prior to the 1971 Pacific Coast Longshore Strike. During that strike, he served as a picket captain. While at ILWU Local 10, Allen also served on the Promotions Commitee. During this period, Allen worked in various different ports on the Pacific Coast, incluing Los Angeles, Portland, and Tacoma.
Later, Allen used the ILWU transfer program to transfer to the growing port of Tacoma, where he became a member of ILWU, Local 23.
During his time in Tacoma's Local 23, Allen formed a coalition with other transferred longshoremen from the Portland local (ILWU Local 8), and advocated reforms in the union's handling of the dispatch system and the qualification for the test necessary to become a crane operator--a coveted job. Eventually, these transfers from Portland and San Francisco began to reform Local 23's internal political culture, winning offices as the local's president, vice president, on the Longshore Relations Committee, as walking bosses, as clerks, and as crane operators--all positions of esteem and influence in the local. Allen also became an internal advocate for union militancy and policing of the contract and working conditions; filing and assisting other members in filing grievances. Allen was also involved in a gender discrimination grievance and lawsuit by Linda Nyland against the Local 23 and the Pacific Martime Association (the employers' organization).
Allen later retired from ILWU 23 and remains living in Tacoma.
Research materials and correspondence collected by Al Allen and created and collected by Allen or Stanley Weir. Correspondence in the collection includes articles on the longshore industry and its workers by Herb Mills as well as correspondence from Mills to Allen. Subject files and reports include information on the impact of techonology on the longshore industry, including containerization and mechanization, and its impact on workers. Other files and reports includes studies on longshore decasualization, the hiring hall, and the mechanization of the Port of Rotterdam by Sidney Roger. Several VHS tapes are included in the collection, including information on the life of Bill Bailey and talks by David Arian and others on longshore issues and history.
Forms part of the Labor Archives of Washington.
DVD viewing copy of "LifeStory: Bill Bailey" by Maria Brooks digitized and available via a viewing copy.
No restrictions on access. VHS cassette of "LifeStory: Bill Bailey" should not be played; instead the DVD access copy should be used.
Al Allen, 2016-05-11.
International Longshore and Warehouse Union.; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Labor unions$zUnited States.; Labor$zUnited States.; Labor movement$zUnited States.; General strikes$zUnited States.; Hiring halls$zUnited States.; Stevedores$zUnited States.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.)$vSpecimens.; Business correspondence.; Video recordings.
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Ships and Shipping
- Herb Mills papers, circa 1979-1989 (Box-folder 1/1)
- "Same Cargoes Different Cultures" by Sydney Rodgers, March 1976 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Decasualization Studies, 1939 (Box-folder 1/3)
- "Application of the Pacific Maritime Association and The International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union", March 14, 1972 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Contract, 2002 (Box-folder 1/5)
- PMA Lockout, 2002 (Box-folder 1/6)
- "Hiring Halls in the Maritime Industry", 1950 (Box-folder 1/7)
- "The Work Culture of the San Francisco Longshoremen", circa 1974 (Box-folder 1/7)
- "Decasualization of Dock Labor" by Joseph H. Ball, 1966 (Box-folder 1/8)
- American Longshoremen in Rotterdam, 1975 (Box-folder 2/1)
- Congressional Hearing on Hiring Halls, 1950 (Box-folder 2/2)
- Causes of Pay Board, 1972 (Box-folder 2/3)
- ILWU - Copies of "The Dispatch" newspaper, March 2006-February 2016 (Box-folder 2/4)
- "A Study of the Work Culture of San Francisco Longshoremen" by Stan Weir, 1975 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Containerization, November 1959 (Box-folder 2/6)
- HIP Pocket Rules, 1956 (Box-folder 2/7)
- Miscellaneous Clippings and Photocopies, 1979, 1991, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
- Floating Palaces (Ships) - History ACLU, undated; videocassette #14; videocassette
- Pacific Maritime Association - General Safety Training Modules 1-8, undated; videocassette #15; videocassette
- Canadian Area Speeches - Randy Veckich and David Arian, June 12, 1991; videocassette #16; videocassette
- "LifeStory: Bill Bailey" produced by Maria Brooks, undated; videocassette #17; DVD viewing copy of "LifeStory: Bill Bailey" by Maria Brooks digitized and available via a viewing copy.; videocassette